[SPEAKER_00]: This is Anguttara Nikaya 5.27, Samādhi Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a short sutta, but it has some interesting point, points that can be unpacked.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it starts by saying, because develop limitless, intelligent, recollected composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by developing limitless, intelligent, recollected composure, five knowledges arise for oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which five?
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge, the first knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: This composure is currently pleasant and in the future the result will be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The word for pleasant, sukha, so it can also be translated as easy, ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: This composure is currently resulting in ease and any future result will be also the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and that is... it's not... or pleasure, whichever way you were to choose to translate it, it's not... it's not obviously of essential kind, as the Buddha would often describe that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it also... it's not of a physical kind either.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I wanted to say the alternative of ease, because you don't necessarily feel ease specifically as a sensation in your body or something that you can kind of observe in that manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more of a state that's experienced on the existential level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, freedom from threat, for example, is something that would result in you experiencing an ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of that, if you were to surmount, has to result in ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to practice the boundless or limitless type of composure,
[SPEAKER_00]: It would have to result in ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first... first type of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the second type of knowledge is... oh, yeah, it says... this composure is noble, not of the flesh.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... it's not pertaining to sensual ecstatic pleasure or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically on the level of the mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of the mind, and it results in that existential ease from threat, from being prey to suffering, from anything that sort of burdens you, the back of your mind, emotionally, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the third knowledge is that this composure is not associated with inferior men.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means that in order to have this composure, you need to have wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be... it needs to be understood and developed in that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that level, it's not... it's not... it cannot happen to you accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot stumble upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot not be restrained, not make the effort towards that self-strengthening of that composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obtain this type of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything that would make you inferior, which is greed, aversion, delusion, is not something that you can... that can result in this type of knowledge, in this type of composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to abandon the inferiority, in that sense, internally, in order to partake to this knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fourth knowledge is the knowledge that this composure is peaceful, elevated, obtained through calming, reached by unification, not by suppressing, holding back or obstructing saṅkharas, the determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is probably the most condensed line of this sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before we get into it, again, the sutta is called samādhi-sutta, and samādhi is composure, it's not concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have composure without a colloquial sense of concentration, but obviously you can't have concentration without composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But samādhi is much more than just concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: And more often than not, practically speaking, when people take, or when people think of concentration, you think about focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: By definition, that's what concentrating is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Focusing on a particular object at the expense of everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Samādhi is opposite of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: We said that many times before, but it doesn't hurt to repeat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's composing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's bringing things together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not excluding everything on account of one point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, basically, developing the type of composure that doesn't exclude any fundamental aspects of your experience, such as perception, feeling, intentions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's addressed in many other suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to keep reiterating that, because, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people would waste tremendous amount of effort in just concentrating and concentrating and expecting a certain, like, a release, an experience to come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But samādhi is opposite of focusing on one point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, basically, one point limits you.
[SPEAKER_00]: One point is limiting and one point is your boundary.
[SPEAKER_00]: You focusing on sensations, the tip of your nostrils, belly, whatever meditation object you might have taken, means you're doing it at the expense of everything else, as I mentioned before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that cannot be called limitless and boundless.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing boundless about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're bound, literally, by one point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite direction of common assumption of concentration practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why samādhi and mindfulness, hand in hand, one results in the other, it fortifies it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, composure, that is intelligent, based on wisdom, based on mindfulness, based on recollectedness, as the opening lines of this, so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to keep that in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that general recollectiveness that then you sort of fortify into a sense of composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, like, compose yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody just tells you...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, putting aside anything you know, you think you might know, anything you heard about meditation, if somebody were to tell you, compose yourself, how would you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you do it by focusing on your nostrils or soles of your feet?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would just bring yourself back into your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, recognize that you couldn't have left it, even if you wanted to, and that you're fully enclosed by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, compose yourself and stop ignoring your current experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, if fully developed, samādhi will have to uproot the attitude of ignoring, which is what the vijja is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring things of the unpleasant kind, usually.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, composure, then, means bringing yourself together, recollecting yourself, keeping yourself composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you practice that, the more it's going to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fourth knowledge is recognition that this type of composure is peaceful, elevated, got through calming, reached by unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Calming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Calm yourself down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know how to do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you recognize what to attend, how to attend?
[SPEAKER_00]: They will have to result in calmness, or do you just go through a set of motions that sort of approximate the idea of what calmness is, and then you hope calmness will happen to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if it's the latter, it means you're not doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to develop samādhi where you know
[SPEAKER_00]: What calmness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know how to do it, and you know how to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will have to calm you from anything that has been disturbing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this composure is peaceful, elevated, got through calming, reached by unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, again, how do you unify things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you unify things by focusing on one point that excludes everything else?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's separation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you unify it by not taking up a point, an object of your meditation, and discerning just universal nature of whatever you're experiencing at the time?
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes your container, and by definition, that's already a form of unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you unify all these diverse aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these feelings that I feel throughout the day, well, you unify them by being composed upon the nature of felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter on account of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how diverse feelings might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a form of unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this composure is peaceful, elevated, go through calming, reached by unification, not by suppressing, holding back, pretty much concentrating and obstructing the determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what determinations is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing what things are there that determine your calmness or determine your lack of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing what is there in your experience as a whole that undermines your composure or establishes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, knowledge of determinations means knowledge of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing how to attend determinations in sankhāras means, basically, knowing how to practice samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the fifth knowledge is, I entered upon this meditation, this type of composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this composure, I'm not going to say type, because this is the composure that the Buddha approves of, which means that's the composure that should be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: No other type of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fifth knowledge is that I enter upon this composure with recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I emerge from it with recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it does not just happen to you, so you don't have a clue how this boundless composure has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know exactly how it came to be, and you know exactly when it's ceasing to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: I enter upon it with recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fully recollected.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no lapsing in your mindfulness, in your establishment upon experience as a whole, establishment of your mind, when you enter this boundlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it's not a mystical experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not experience of some, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: Undescribable, indescribable sense of cessation and boundlessness and limitless and that you can't put in the words.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can very well put it in the words and the Buddha just did.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said these are the five knowledges that you can use to describe this very type of composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fundamental characteristic is there is absolutely no compromising of your mindfulness, of your recollectedness, of your sati.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the basis for this composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even when you leave this composure, that sati remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is sati, if there is composure upon sati, there is no focusing practice of concentration upon one thing or the other, and then having this lofty, extraordinarily pleasant experience come over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, possess you for a while, and then it's just ecstatic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or extremely pleasant, whichever way you want to describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure means ease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Composure means opposite of concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: Based upon recollectedness, it requires wisdom, because it cannot be obtained by inferior men.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's noble, not of the flesh, does not pertain to anything that you can feel pleasantly by any of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can only be entered upon through mindfulness, through recollectedness, and emerge from it on the basis of recollectedness.